Guide to the Dean and Fanny Wickes Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Dean and Fanny Wickes Papers
1908-1943
RG 257
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(9 boxes)
Dean and Fanny Wickes were missionaries serving in Shandong from 1912 to 1934 under the North China Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. Correspondence, writings, photographs, and collected material document the life and work of these missionaries who were engaged in educational and evangelistic work.
Wickes, Dean Rockwell
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mark Waldrop, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1883 September 10 Dean Rockwell Wickes born in Granville, Ohio
1905 Graduated from the University of Chicago, having received a Senior College Scholarship for excellence in the Department of Geology, and Phi Beta Kappa (1904)
1908 Received Master's degree from Yale University
1909 Received B.D. from Yale Divinity School
1912 Received Ph.D. from the University of Chicago, with focus on New Testament and Religious Education
1912 August 24 Married Fanny Rollinson Sweeny, daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Louis LaBaume Sweeny
1912 Dean and Fanny appointed missionaries of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions and sailed to China, where they were stationed first in Peking [Beijing] for language study and then at the ABCFM station in T'ungchou/T'unghsien [Tongxian] as of September, 1913, where Dean taught at North China Union College. Summers were spent at the missionary retreat area in Peitaiho [Beidaihe].
1917 August 7 Daughter Alice born
1918-1919 Family based in Peking [Beijing], Dean teaching at Theological College
1919-1920 Family on furlough in U.S., Dean studying at Union Theological Seminary, New York
1920 Return to China; family based in T'unghsien [Tongxian]
1922 Death of infant daughter Mary Frances
1923 October 26 Birth of daughter Margaret
1925 October Family moved to Lintsing [Linqing]
1926 Birth of daughter Eleanor
1927-1928 Furlough in U.S.; Dean studying at Union Theological Seminary, New York, received S.T.M. degree
1928 Return to China; based in Lintsing [Linqing]; Dean at Ellis Layman's Christian Training School
1933 Family moves to Tehchow [Dezhou] as Lintsing station closes
1934 Family informed that ABCFM can no longer support them in China; Dean returns to U.S. and finds job at Library of Congress
1935 Fanny and Eleanor in in Los Angeles; move to Washington, D.C. in August; Dean is employed by Research Division of Soil Erosion, Department of Agriculture
1935 November Death of Fanny Wickes
Scope and Contents
The Dean and Fanny Wickes papers provide valuable documentation of their work as missionaries of the North China Mission of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions during the years 1912 to 1934. The Wickes were well-educated individuals dedicated to their work in China. Their letters home to their parents are detailed and substantial, with a focus on recounting their daily activities and surroundings in China.The Wickes papers complement other collections held at the Yale Divinity Library, including fellow North China Mission missionaries Earle and Thelma Ballou, Constance Buell, Emery Ellis, Lewis and Lois Gilbert, James and Maude Hunter, Helen Kintner, Harold Matthews, Alice Reed, Olga Robinson, and Ernest Shaw.
The Family Correspondence of Series I is primarily from the Wickes to their parents, a regular series of detailed letters. General Correspondence includes letters to and from colleagues in China.
Series II provides fairly sparse biographical documentation but does include family photograph albums and statements by the Wickes regarding their faith and work.
The Mission-related Collected Material of Series III provides insight into issues and concerns of the American Board mission during this era of political disruption in China and financial stress for missions.
Series IV contains a number of interesting reflections by both Dean and Fanny Wickes on their work and on events and customs in China. Some of these writings were published and others prepared to inform their supporters in the U.S.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1908-1943
II. Biographical Documentation and Memorabilia, 1908-1936
III. Mission-related Collected Material, 1916-1934
IV. Writings and Notes, 1912-1934
Mission -- China; Wickes, Dean Rockwell; Wickes, Fanny Sweeny; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Dean and Fanny Wickes to/from their parents
      Scope and Contents
      Letters are primarily from Dean and Fanny to their parents. In later years there are some letters of their daughter Alice and from the parents.
      - Dean (DW) attending Yale Divinity School, 1908 Oct (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - DW at YDS: campus life, assignments, sermon preparation, 1909 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - DW at YDS: attending China mission class, working on thesis, 1909 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - DW graduates from YDS; visits to extended family members before return to Chicago, 1909 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Re. travels in U.S. and enroute to China, with stop in Honolulu, 1912 May-Oct (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Continuation of trip to China with stop in Japan, arrival in Peking [Beijing]; language study, 1912 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Daily life in China; exploration of Peking, 1913 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Life in Peking; Empress Dowager's death and funeral, 1913 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Life in Peking; to summer resort in Peitaiho [Beidaihe], 1913 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Summer activities in Peitaiho, 1913 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Move to T'ungchou [Tongxian]; DW teaching singing class; accounts of Chinese customs, 1913 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - In T'ungchou: missionaries' "Pastimes Club", government unrest, Christmas celebrations, 1913 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - In T'ungchou: study, teaching, travel to other mission stations, 1914 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Travel to Lintsing [Linqing], teaching in Chinese; District meeting in Peking, travel to Peitaiho, 1914 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - In Peitaiho; purchase of house there, 1914 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 14a)
      - Return to T'ungchou and teaching; DW chairman of Music Committee; flooding in area; Christmas trip to Peking, 1914 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Re. school life and teaching; severe dust storms in area, 1915 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - To Peking for District Association meetings; visit to Great Wall and Ming Tombs; DW appointed superintendent of boys' school, 1915 Apr-Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Summer activities in Peitaiho; return to T'ungchou, 1915 Jul-Sep (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - DW submits resignation as superintendent of boys' school following incident of dismissal of students for demanding a change of Classics teacher; FW travels to country station, 1915 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - In T'ungchou; visit to Forbidden City; copy of mandate issued by Yuan Shih Kai, 1916 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - FW visits country fair for evangelism; school life, 1916 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Death of Yuan Shih Kai; to Peitaiho for summer, 1916 Jun-Jul (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Return to T'ungchou; FW's mother arrives for visit, 1916 Aug-Oct (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - School life; preparations for holidays, 1916 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - FW's mother returns to U.S.; some students leave school to work in France and Britain during war; DW chairs committee to celebrate 50 years of Christian work in T'ungchou, 1917 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - College at T'ungchou to be moved to Peking as part of federated university; travel to Peitaiho for summer, 1917 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Birth of daughter Alice on August 7, 1917 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Re. life in T'ungchou; Alice's growth, 1917 Sep-Dec
      - T'ungchou changed to T'unghsien; evangelism trips, 1918 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - DW trip to Paoti to pay laborers and evangelize; planning joint missions at University of Peking; travel to Peitaiho for summer, 1918 Apr-Jul (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - DW returns to T'unghsien for Teachers' Institute; family moves to Peking; DW teaching at Theological College, 1918 Aug-Oct (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Celebrations for peace in China and end of European war; teaching activities; plans for furlough, 1918 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Teaching in Peking; Provincial Association meetings; furlough plans, 1919 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Return to U.S. for furlough; DW studying at Union Theological Seminary, 1919 Jun-Dec (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - DW studying at Union Theological Seminary, 1920 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Return to China; stationed in T'unghsien with trips to countryside, including Chang Hsin Tien, 1920 May-Dec (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - DW in Tai Shui and elsewhere doing relief work; extreme poverty in area; daughter Mary Frances born, 1921 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - DW ill with measles; continues relief work; to Peitaiho for summer, 1921 May-Dec (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Based in T'unghsien with evangelistic trips to out-stations; whooping cough at station, 1922 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Daughter Mary Frances dies of cerebral meningitis; family to Peitaiho for summer; DW makes country trips; political and military unrest in area, 1922 Jun-Dec (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - DW on country preaching trip; 50th anniversary of Paotingfu station; teaching, 1923 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Planning summer conference in WoFoSsu; to Peitaiho for summer, 1923 May-Jul (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Return to T'unghsien; birth of daughter Margaret on October 20, 1923 Aug-Oct (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - DW visiting villages and market towns; sings with Peking Choral Society, 1923 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Preaching trips to countryside, 1924 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Association meetings; village visits, 1924 Apr-May (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Family at Peitaiho; DW teaching summer school in Peking; flooding in area, 1924 Jun-Aug (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Return to T'unghsien; DW doing relief work following floods; political unrest adds to difficulties; DW resumes country trips, 1924 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - T'unghsien city police and Governor of Metropolitan District start Christian meetings for staff; Association meeting includes discussion re. Wickes family moving to Lintsing station, 1925 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - DW resumes country trips; to Peitaiho for summer, 1925 Apr-Jul (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Wickes family moves to Lintsing in October; DW takes country trip, 1925 Aug-Oct (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Training School for Laymen established; DW teaching a three year course, 1925 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Based in Lintsing; DW teaching at Bible school; military unrest in area, 1926 Jan-Feb (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Opening of training school for practical service in the community; 40th anniversary of mission work in Lintsing, 1926 Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Council meetings in Tientsin [Tianjin]; DW's book "Flowers of Peitaiho" published; to Peitaiho for summer, 1926 May-Jul (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - DW to summer conference in Tehchow; to Ching Ping to organize a church; daughter Eleanor born October 13, 1926 Aug-Oct (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Furlough plans; women and children ordered to leave Lintsing due to incident in Nanking; FW and girls go to Tientsin, then Korea, 1927 Jan-Apr (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - DW remains in China to finish up work; family sails to U.S. from Kobe, Japan in June; travel to NY, visiting FW's family, 1927 May-Dec (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - DW studying at Union Seminary; family in Poughkeepsie, 1928 Jan-Apr (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - DW graduates from Union Seminary; family travels to CA and leaves for China, 1928 May-Sep (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Based in Lintsing; school resumes; DW visits village to examine candidates for church membership; electricity installed in home, 1928 Oct-Dec (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - DW to Peking for meetings; family to Peitaiho; new building for training school; trip to country station, 1919 Jan-Jul (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Summer conference; problems with bandits; teaching, family life, 1929 Aug-Dec (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - DW at conference in Peking; life in Lintsing, includes letters from daughter Alice at North China American School to her grandparents, 1930 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - DW to country for visit; Fanny and children to Peitaiho in May; new grain seeds bring better harvest, 1930 Apr-Jun (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - DW returns to Lintsing for conference; illness prevents return to Peitaiho; FW has operation in Peking, 1930 Aug-Oct (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - Military unrest in area; Fanny and girls return to Lintsing; holiday celebrations, 1930 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - DW teaching; country trips; family life and illnesses, 1931 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - DW teaching; letters from Alice; to Peitaiho for summer; mission-related meetings, 1931 Apr-Jul (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Incl. letters regarding the Tehchow incident when Dr. Tucker killed a robber at mission hospital, 1931 Aug-Oct (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Teaching and country trips; holiday celebrations, 1931 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 71)
      - DW busy with committee meetings, travel, 1932 Jan-Feb (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - Planning for conference on 5 year movement emphasizing literacy and rural needs; DW supervising student trips to rural groups, 1932 Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - Proposal to combine Lintsing and Tehchow stations; family to Peitaiho, DW in Lintsing, 1932 May-Jun (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - DW teaches class at Cheeloo University; joins family in Peitaiho; Fanny has surgery in Peking before return to Lintsing, 1932 Jul-Sep (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - DW establishes village school in Wang Chia Li Chuang; plan for health work in country center; holiday celebrations, 1932 Oct-Dec (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - Lintsing and Tehchow stations to be merged; DW in Pi Hsueh Tien for extended session of classes, 1933 Jan-Mar
      - Approach of Japanese troops delays Council meeting; Alice's school closes early, 1933 Apr-May (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - DW to Peiping for North China Council meeting; Lintsing personnel to move to Tehchow; family to Peitaiho, 1933 Jun-Aug (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - FW chairing Evangelistic Committee; family moves to Tehchow; DW makes country trip, 1933 Sep-Dec (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Wickes informed that they are "withdrawn" from mission due to financial concerns, 1934 Mar-May (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - Planning for return to U.S.; DW sails first for job search; gets job at Library of Congress Division of Orientalia; FW and Eleanor sail to U.S.; Alice and Margaret remain in school in China, 1934 Jul-Dec (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - FW living in Los Angeles with DW's father; DW appointed to Research Division of Soil Erosion, Department of Agriculture, 1935 Jan-Apr (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - FW and girls move to Washington DC in August; FW dies in November, 1935 May-Dec (Box 5, Folder 86)
      - Re. DW and daughters in Washington; Alice attending Oberlin College; DW remarries, 1936 Jan - 1940 Apr (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Dean and Fanny Wickes letters to each other
      - Early meetings; Fanny attending Vassar College, 1909 Sep - 1912 May (Box 5, Folder 88)
      - Married and living in China; travels, daily life while apart, 1920 Dec - 1927 Jul (Box 5, Folder 89)
      - Letters written from Lintsing, T'ungchou, Peitaiho, 1930 May-Oct (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - Letters written from Lintsing, Peitaiho, T'ungchou, 1931 Feb-Sep (Box 6, Folder 91)
      - Letters written from Lintsing, Peiping, 1933 Mar-Dec (Box 6, Folder 93)
      - DW in Chiang Chun Chai; FW shares news of their being dropped by mission; DW returns to U.S. to look for job; FW and Eleanor in California, 1934 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 94)
      - DW appointed to Soil Erosion Service, Department of Agriculture; plans for FW and Eleanor to move to DC, 1935 Jan-Apr (Box 6, Folder 95)
      - Alice and Margaret arrive from China; DW finds house for family in DC; preparations for moving, 1935 May-Aug (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Dean and Fanny Wickes to extended family
      - To/from FW's brother and sister, 1917-1934 (Box 6, Folder 97)
      - From uncles William Wickes and Tom Wickes, 1913-1935 (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - From aunts Alice, Belle, Emily, Fannie, Margaret, Mary, Lizzie and cousin Alice, 1911-1935 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - General correspondence
    - Dean and Fanny Wickes to/from others
      - A-C: Arnold, Baldwin, Ballou, Chandler, Chang, Charlie, Cross, 1906-1935 (Box 6, Folder 100)
      - D-G: Dundes, Ewing, Fairfield, Fifield, Fleming, Grimes, 1919-1935 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - H-Le: Hemingway, Hubbard, Hugh, Hummel, Jacoby, Latourette, Lewis, 1927-1935 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Li-M: Li, Lobenstine, Lois, Lyons, Martin, Murphy, 1927-1935 (Box 6, Folder 103)
      - N-St: Nelson, North, Palmer, Richards, Robinson, Stelle, Steward, 1912-1935 (Box 6, Folder 104)
      - Su-Y: Sun, Tsur, Tsen, Upton, Whitaker, While, William, Wilson, Winans, Yung, 1911-1935 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Letters of others
      - A-M: Alice, Ballou, Bergen, Cooke, Cross, Darrow, Fairfield, Graves, Grimes, Murphy, 1927-1943 (Box 7, Folder 106)
      - R-W: Robinson, Shaw, Stevens, Sweeney, William Wickes, 1927-1943 (Box 7, Folder 107)
- Biographical Documentation and Memorabilia, Series II
  - Regarding marriage, education, Fanny's will, later employment, 1908-1936 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Travel to China, medical letters, personal and household accounts, 1912-1932 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Diary, lists of property left with missionaries, miscellaneous, 1930-1934 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Family photographs; Fanny, Dean, daughters, scenes - album and loose photos, 1912-1924 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Family photographs: Albums for Eleanor and Mary Frances, 1931-1934 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Chinese language materials (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - Newsclippings (Box 9, Folder 125)
  - Programs for concerts, etc. (Box 9, Folder 126)
  - Invitations; re. Vassar College (Box 9, Folder 127)
  - Memorabilia (Box 9, Folder 128)
- Mission-related Collected Material, Series III
  - Reports of Lintsing Memorial Hospital (1928, 1929), Ellis Christian Training School; American Board statements and reports, 1927-1933 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Regarding evacuation of missionaries in 1927; ordination of Pastor Chi Kua Tung; record book of various schools and people, 1916-1934 (Box 7, Folder 114)
- Writings and Notes, Series IV
  - Notebooks
    - Impressions of early days in China, studying Chinese, 1912-1923 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Notes about conference speakers; ideas for work and policy, 1923-1928 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Notes about Chinese men; daily notes regarding work, village work in Pi Hsueh Tien, 1930-1934 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Essays/notes
    These are primarily typescript and handwritten notes and essays by Dean and Fanny Wickes, in some cases reports to their supporters. Authorship of some writings is unclear.
    - Including "The Winter Palace of Peking", "In Peking", "Getting Started in the Work" by FW, 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Including "The Cult of Blood" (published in Peking Gazette)by FW, "The College and the Academy" (re. North China Union College), "The Work of the TungChou Station", 1914-1916 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Including ""The Touch of the West", Report of FW's visit to Third Moon Fair; "Report on Educational Work in Tungchou", "Language and its Study", "Notes on General Conditions", 1916 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Including ""Our Colleagues", "Soldiers and Christian Soldiers in China", "A Festive Evening in Tunghsien", "A Jingle of Chinese History", "Notes on Tungchou Temples", "The Everyday Life of a Common Chinese Woman", 1917-1922 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Including newsletter from Goodrich Girls' School, Tunghsien, "Bound Feet and Free", "Peking Industries", sermons, 1923-1925 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Including "They Are Hungry for the Gospel of Jesus Christ", "Our Answer" (poem re. their withdrawal from mission), excerpts from letter to North China Council, 1927-1934 (Box 8, Folder 123)